<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Personal on Yengas</title>
    <link>https://blog.yigitcan.dev/categories/personal/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Personal on Yengas</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 20 Nov 2016 16:30:00 +0300</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://blog.yigitcan.dev/categories/personal/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>How I Made This Blog?</title>
      <link>https://blog.yigitcan.dev/personal-website/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Nov 2016 16:30:00 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.yigitcan.dev/personal-website/</guid>
      <description>After the release of Github Actions i refactored this project to work with it instead of wercker. Blog posts and configuration for the Hugo is stored under the source branch of Yengas/yengas.github.io, Github Actions builds and pushes html/css/js files on the master branch of the same repository.
I haven&amp;rsquo;t been designing any GUI&amp;rsquo;s since i switched from Web development to other platforms. Most of the projects i&amp;rsquo;ve worked on for the last few years were either single page designs, or they worked in the background.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>https://blog.yigitcan.dev/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.yigitcan.dev/about/</guid>
      <description>Hello, I&amp;rsquo;m Yiğitcan! For over a decade, I&amp;rsquo;ve been involved in software development, working with both corporate and startup companies, developing for different platforms like web, mobile, and desktop. Typescript, NodeJS, Golang, and Java are some of the technologies I frequently use.
Building meaningful products as a team is one of my favorite things to do. Whether it&amp;rsquo;s designing backend architecture, engaging with cloud-native technologies, or experimenting with something new, learning and solving problems together is what motivates me most in the software world.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
